Guide to University of Chicago Library Exhibit Publications Collection 1964-2009
University of Chicago Library
- Eva Watson Schutze and the Philosophers' Circle, Eva Watson Schutze was a founding member of the Photo-Secession, a turn-of-the-century movement led by Alfred Steglitz that sought to establish photography as one of the fine arts. Also referred to as "pictorialists," its members distinguished themselves from representational photographers who aimed to record as precisely as possible the appearance of persons, places, and objects. Rather, pictorialists regarded their work as a vehicle for creative artistic expression. Although Schutze is familiar to students of the Photo-Secession, her later life and work remained a mystery until 1979, when a number of photographs bearing Schutze's distinctive signature were added to the papers of philosophers James Hayden Tufts and George Herbert Mead collected in the University of Chicago Archives. While these works are invaluable for students of the history of photography, the Eva Watson Schutze Collection also graphically reveals the extensive web of social and intellectual relationships existing between some of the University's most notable faculty, their families, and their associates. The exhibit includes letters, diaries and memoirs which illuminate these relationships and also serve to place the remarkable photographs displayed in this exhibit. Special Collections Research Center January 1, 1985 – April 1, 1985
- The Book Made Art: A Selection of Contemporary Artists' Books, Composed almost entirely of unique books created between 1976 and 1986 in the United States, England and on the European Continent, the exhibit focuses on the transformation of the artistic book from decorated text to sculptural object. Nearly fifty examples colorfully and dramatically challenge familiar expectations of linear progression, text, and physical presentation in the book form. The books in the exhibition challenge traditional notions of the codex form through the use of electricity, the continuous film-strip, embroidery, glass, ceramic, and various other media. Special Collections Research Center February 1, 1986 – May 1, 1986
- William Benton: A Public Life, This exhibition, based primarily on the William Benton Papers in the University of Chicago Archives, examines the range and substance of Benton's contributions within a number of distinct but interlocking spheres: founder of Benton and Bowles, vice-president and trustee of the University of Chicago, pioneer in educational films and radio, owner and publisher of the Encyclopaedia Britannica, Muzak entrepreneur, unofficial advisor to the isolationist America First Committee, charter member and vice-chairman of the Committee for Economic Development, Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs, founding delegate to UNESCO, liberal Senator from Connecticut, opponent of Joseph McCarthy, and creator of the Benton Foundation for philanthropy in education and communications. Special Collections Research Center January 1, 1987 – May 1, 1987
- Huidobro in avant-garde [an exhibition in the Department of Special Collections, the Joseph Regenstein Library, the University of Chicago, Winter 1988], This major exhibition of photographs, manuscripts and books traces the life and work of the avant-garde poet Vicente Huidobo (1893-1948). Drawn primarily from the poet's personal papers in the family archive in Chile, the exhibition examines the complex relationship that developed between Huidobo and his compatriots-Pablo Picasso, Juan Gris, Jacques Lipchitz, among others-as they collectively forged modernist idioms in poetry, painting, and sculpture in the first two decades of the twentieth century. In the course of his highly productive lifetime Huidobo embarked on myriad projects: he left a large corpus of poetry and made fundamental contributions to modernist theory, he started several modernist literary journals, collaborated with Robert and Sonia Delaunay on the creation of "poetry-to-be-worn" (garments emblazoned with his poetry), wrote the script for a prize-winning "Cubist" motion picture (Cagliostro). Participated in the Spanish Civil War in the fight against fascism, and understood an ill-fated bid for the presidency of Chile. The exhibit was organized by RenŽ de Costa, Professor of Romance Language and Literature at the University of Chicago. Special Collections Research Center January 1, 1988 – March 1, 1988
- Great Is the Gift that Bringeth Knowledge: Highlights from the History of the John Crerar Library, Marking the 100th anniversary of the death of John Crerar, the exhibition utilized documents, photographs, and artifacts from the Crerar collections to chronicle the library's distinguished collections and effective public service programs from its creation until the merger with the University of Chicago. Special Collections Research Center October 1, 1989 – April 1, 1989
- Encyclopedism from Pliny to Borges, The exhibit, highlighting 77 volumes from the Special Collections Research Center, traces the variety of forms the encyclopedia and the idea of encyclopedic knowledge have taken from the first through 20th centuries. Including rare volumes ranging from the first edition of the Encyclopaedia Brittanica (1773) to Museum Wormianum (1655) compiled by Ole Worm, a Danish doctor and natural scientist who catalogues his own collection of Scandinavian Artifacts. The exhibit was researched and curated by Paolo Cherchi, Professor of Romance Languages and Literatures, and Barbara Stafford, Professor of Art, as part of a proposed conference on encyclopedias and their impact on cultural forms. Special Collections Research Center May 1, 1990 – September 30, 1990
- Animal-Vegetable-Mineral: Natural History Illustration from the John Crerar Collection, The art and beauty of illustrated natural history books is celebrated in this exhibition. Drawn exclusively from the John Crerar Collection of Rare Books in the History of Science and Medicine, the exhibition features more than 80 illustrated works from the 15th through the 20th centuries. The collection exemplifies the development of natural history illustration and the role of the image in disseminating knowledge of the natural sciences. Special Collections Research Center May 1, 1991 – September 30, 1991
- Asia in the Eyes of Europe: Sixteenth through Eighteenth Centuries, This exhibition examines one of the most important and enduring themes in Western thought. From the time of the Renaissance onward, Western consciousness has been shaped by a multitude of diverse and rapidly changing images of Asia and its peoples. Explorers, traders, missionaries, and scholars returned from the East with stories of strange plants, animals, and cultures beyond the limits of European experience. Incorporated within developing fields of knowledge from astronomy to botany, these reports formed the basis of new and constantly altered visions of what lay beyond the Eastern horizon. In many important ways, the process of Western exploration and discovery of Asia continues to the present day. From the Persian Gulf to Vietnam to China, the West is still contending with a host of powerful and barely-understood images conjured by the ancient cultures of the East. Special Collections Research Center January 1, 1991 – May 31, 1991
- The Un-German Spirit: The Nazi Assault on Arts and Letters, More than 80 items from the Ludwig Rosenberger Library of Judaica as well as the University of Chicago Library are included in this exhibition written by Sem Sutter. The exhibition documents the attempt by German National Socialists of the 1930s to eradicate German avant-garde art, music, literature, theater, and film. This exhibition is accompanied by a pamphlet which includes a bibliography. Special Collections Research Center July 1, 1991 – February 1, 1992
- The University of Chicago Faculty: A Centennial View, The University of Chicago Faculty: A Centennial View" examines the careers of twenty-eight representative scholars from the institution's first century. The 60-page, illustrated catalogue, The University of Chicago Faculty: A Centennial View (Chicago: University of Chicago Library, 1991), was researched and written by Frank Yoder and edited by Daniel Meyer with the Assistance of Richard Popp. Kim Coventry directed the design and production of the exhibition and catalogue. Special Collections Research Center October 1, 1992 – December 1, 1992
- The Presidents of the University of Chicago: A Centennial View, This exhibition, the fourth in a series marking the Centennial of the University of Chicago, examines the distinctive contributions of each of the ten chief executives of the university over the past century. Special Collections Research Center Oct. 1, 1992 – Feb. 1, 1993
- Pursuing the "Higher Criticism": New Testament Scholarship and Library Collections at the University of Chicago, This exhibition traces the century-long partnership between Chicago New Testament research interests and library resources. Drawing on the Library's outstanding holdings of New Testament sources, the exhibition examines the contributions of New Testament scholars to their field and the library collections that support their work. Among the topics covered are the empirical approach to biblical studies characteristic of the Chicago School and the influence of methodologies from other disciplines such as sociology and history. Included in the exhibition are Greek New Testament manuscripts and early printed books used as sources for New Testament textual, critical, and iconographical study, as well as archival materials and published works illustrating the research interests of Chicago New Testament scholars such as Ernest DeWitt Burton, Edgar J. Goodspeed, Shirley Jackson Case, Shailer Mathews, Robert M. Grant, Hans Dieter Betz, and others. Special Collections Research Center July 1, 1993 – October 1, 1993
- Eugene Field and His Books, Eugene Field (1850 - 1895) was a major figure in Chicago's literary and book collecting circles at the time of his death 100 years ago. He was a very popular author, nationally known for his newspaper column, "Sharps and Flats," his humorous stories and verse for children. "Eugene Field and his Books" marks the centenary of Field's death and the founding of Chicago's Caxton Club. The exhibition, which includes manuscripts, correspondence, limited editions and other materials from the private collection of Frank J. Piehl (Ph.D., 1952) and the holdings of the University of Chicago Library, focuses on Field as author, collector and promoter of books and the book arts. Special Collections Research Center December 1, 1994 – March 1, 1995
- Wrapped in Color: A Survey of Paste Paper Bookbindings, This exhibition, selected and written by Sem Sutter, traces the development of "paste papers", the colorful decorative papers produced by bookbinders and other artisans from the late sixteenth century to the present. Special Collections Research Center March 1, 1994 – June 1, 1994
- Montaigne in Print: The Presentation of a Renaissance Text, Featuring editions of the Essais by French philosopher Michel de Montaigne, this exhibition explores the relationship between author, editor, printer, and the book as a physical object by tracing the bibliographic history of the text and its presentation. The exhibition was curated by Professor Philippe Desan and graduate student Arnaud Coulombel, both of the Department of Romance Languages and Literatures. A substantial catalog was published jointly as a special issue of the journal Montaigne Studies. Special Collections Research Center October 1, 1995 – March 1, 1996
- 1900: Books from the Collection of Robert Rosenthal, Featuring books published in the year 1900 that were collected by the late Robert Rosenthal, curator of Special Collections from 1953 to 1989, this exhibition recaptures the forgotten culture of the turn of the century. The books are on loan from Robert Rosenthal's widow, Jane Rosenthal. Suzy Taraba curated the exhibition, and a checklist has been published. Special Collections Research Center January 1, 1996 – May 31, 1996
- From Dreamland to Showcase: Jazz in Chicago, 1912 to 1996, This show highlights the development of jazz music and musicians in the greater Chicago area through the use of sheet music, photographs, recordings, music manuscripts, posters and other treasures from the University Library's Chicago Jazz Archive and from private collections. It celebrates the twentieth anniversary of the Chicago Jazz Archive, which the University established in 1976 as a research collection devoted to the acquisition and preservation of primary source materials relating to jazz in Chicago. Special Collections Research Center October 1, 1996 – February 28, 1997
- South Asia at Chicago: Fifty Years of Scholarship, Modern American scholarship on the Indian subcontinent took root a half-century ago as India and Pakistan were becoming modern nation states. This exhibition appears in conjunction with global events marking the 50th anniversary of Indian and Pakistani independence on August 15, 1947. The U.S. government first began to take a practical interest in area studies in the late 1940s. World War II caused government officials to view American universities and their scholars as a national resource and forced America to consider more closely regions of the world with which it had not previously been engaged, particularly Asia. Research and scholarship in the post-war era contributed to changing attitudes, and with increased interest and financial support from both the government and private American foundations, the new field of South Asian studies emerged. During the same fifty years, the University of Chicago Library collections expanded dramatically to meet the needs of scholars in the University's premier South Asian studies program. This exhibition explores the fabric of interactions between Library resources and Chicago scholars as they have shaped the direction of research on the Indian subcontinent. Rare older publications and recent imprints linked to current faculty and student research projects are displayed. Archival and manuscript materials from the formative years of the University's focus on languages and civilizations of the region are exhibited along with the 500,000th volume added to the Library's South Asia holdings. Special Collections Research Center September 1, 1997 – January 31, 1998
- Frederic Chopin and His Publishers, First and early editions of scores by Frédéric Chopin are featured in this exhibition surveying the relationship between his music and its publishing history. The exhibition includes first editions, images of Chopin and his associates; facsimiles of autograph manuscripts; and later editions prepared by Chopin's students and performers of his music. "Frédéric Chopin and His Publishers" is drawn from the University of Chicago Library's distinguished collection of some 285 first and early editions of Chopin's scores. Because of inconsistencies in contemporary copyright laws, nearly all of Chopin's works had to be issued simultaneously by publishers in France, Germany, and England in order to discourage piracy. Moreover, Chopin was inconsistent about including performance details, which he felt were not fixed elements of his music, in his manuscripts; and he often changed his mind in proofs. As a result, modern performers, editors, and scholars must compare an array of manuscript and printed sources in order to understand what Chopin intended. Most of the manuscripts and nearly all corrected proofs have disappeared, so the first editions are the primary sources for establishing the text of Chopin's music. Editing Chopin's works continues to this day, and the early editions remain essential sources. The exhibition illustrates how its publication history affects the way we hear and understand Chopin's music. Special Collections Research Center February 1, 1998 – April 30, 1998
- Reading the Greens: Books on Golf from the Arthur W. Schultz Collection, Books and other printed golf materials displayed in this exhibition were drawn from the Arthur W. Schultz Golf Collection, which includes more than 1,600 books on the history of golf presented to the University of Chicago Library by Arthur W. Schultz. Titles in the collection, maintained in the Department of Special Collections, reflect an avid golfer's interest in the historical, social, and technical aspects of the game. Arthur W. Schultz is an alumnus and Life Trustee of the University of Chicago. Special Collections Research Center May 1, 1998 – September 30, 1998
- African-American Studies: Resources in the University of Chicago Library, This exhibition explores the University of Chicago Library's broad array of research materials documenting African-American history and culture. Items in the exhibition are drawn from the Library's General Collection and the holdings of the Department of Special Collections. Selected original and modern editions of key texts, government documents, periodicals, directories, microform publications, maps, recordings, scrapbooks, and manuscripts suggest the wealth of Library resources available for research. Special Collections Research Center February 1, 1999 – June 1, 1999
- Homosexuality in the City: A Century of Research at the University of Chicago, The University of Chicago has become a major center for research in lesbian, gay and queer studies in recent years. This development is usually seen as a product of the social and political advances that lesbians and gay men have achieved during the past several decades, but the study of homosexual life and culture is hardly a new phenomenon at the University. Rather it is a field with a long and complicated history on campus--one that has been shaped as much by the social and political climate of the city and nation as by the disciplinary fields in which it has been pursued. Drawing on archives, manuscripts and books from the University of Chicago Library's collections, this exhibition situates Chicago's pioneering approach to the social and cultural study of homosexuality amid the political and cultural developments of the past century, while simultaneously examining the University's role in the policing of homosexuality in Chicago during this same period. For further information on "Homosexuality in the City," see the article in the University of Chicago Magazine, "Gay Studies at Chicago." Special Collections Research Center September 1, 2000 – December 1, 2000
- Building for a Long Future: The University of Chicago and Its Donors, 1889-1930, This exhibition explores the character and benefactions of the early donors to the University of Chicago. Special Collections Research Center May 1, 2001 – December 31, 2001
- Collecting Western Americana: Books from the Library of John Blew, This exhibition examines the work of several important nineteenth-century publishers who edited historical documents of the American West and made them available to a broad audience of readers and scholars. On display are representative volumes produced by each of these influential editors and publishers of Western Americana. Robert Clarke (1829-1899) of Cincinnati issued the Ohio Valley Historical Series (1868-1871), a selection of significant accounts of events and individuals in the early history of the Ohio River valley. Francis P. Harper (1856-1932), a New York City antiquarian book dealer and publisher, produced distinguished editions of works such as Lewis and Clark's History of the Expedition, Zebulon Pike's Account of Expeditions to the Sources of the Mississippi, and Hiram Martin Chittenden's History of the American Fur Trade in the Far West. Reuben Gold Thwaites (1853-1913), superintendent of the State Historical Society of Wisconsin, founded and edited the Society's published series of Collections, an extensive set of historical texts, many of them originally acquired by his predecessor, Lyman C. Draper. Thwaites also undertook the publication of works such as Alexander Scott Withers' Chronicles of Border Warfare, James' Account of S. H.Long's Expedition, 1819-1820, and a monumental 73-volume edition of The Jesuit Relations and Allied Documents. Books in the exhibition are on loan from the personal library of John Blew, a member of the University of Chicago Library Visiting Committee and Library Society Steering Committee. Special Collections Research Center February 1, 2002 – April 30, 2002
- Encountering the American West: The Ohio River Valley, 1750-1820, Before the Wild West was imagined in popular literature and culture, there was another, earlier American west. Its promise drew soldiers, adventurers, speculators, and common folk from the eastern seaboard across the Appalachian Mountains into the rich lands of the Ohio River Valley and the Bluegrass region of Kentucky. This exhibition explores the fascinating history of this first American west from the beginning of European American settlement to the end of the frontier period. Items on display were selected from materials incorporated in The First American West: The Ohio River Valley, 1750-1820, a grant-funded digital project being developed by the University of Chicago Library in collaboration with the Library of Congress American Memory national digital library program. The organization of the exhibition is shaped by a series of interrelated themes: the contrast between native and European American attitudes toward the land, the encounters and confrontations of the pioneer migration era, the role of politics on the early frontier, and the shaping of Western cultural and social institutions. Books, pamphlets, newspapers, maps, broadsides, and manuscripts in the exhibition illustrate historical strengths of the Reuben T. Durret Collection on Kentucky and the Ohio River Valley and related print and manuscript holdings in the Special Collections Research Center and the General Collection of University of Chicago Library. Special Collections Research Center Febraury 1, 2002 – April 30, 2002
- Between the Boards: Collections, Compilations and Curiosities from the John Crerar Collection of Rare Books in the History of Science and Medicine, Recent developments in digital technology and the work of contemporary book artists have stimulated debates about the nature of a book. Shared assumptions about what will be found "between the boards" persist--a printed or handwritten text, sometimes accompanied by tables, charts, illustrations, or other media. Over 20,000 volumes from the John Crerar Collection of Rare Books in the History of Science and Medicine were recently cataloged, thanks to a gift from University of Chicago Trustee Harvey Plotnick. This exhibition celebrates the completion of the project and the surprising discoveries it made possible. Online records for many landmark books in the history of science and medicine are now fully accessible to researchers. So too are collections of lichen, algae, and wood samples; compilations of clippings and articles on aeronautics; books on anatomy and machines with models and moveable parts; and other novel uses of the book format to communicate and preserve information. The examples on view illustrate the ingenuity of the authors and other compilers, the creative scope of the personal and institutional collectors who brought these items together, the skill of catalogers who described the materials, and the exciting opportunities awaiting researchers. Special Collections Research Center March 1, 2003 – June 30, 2003